[Music]
so Hana you put together a film called
from women to men and it's gone pretty
viral online it's had we think over
about a million views
lots of polarized reactions and you're
as you say in the film what you want is
to start a new conversation between
women and men and in the film it's a you
and a lot of other women including ile
am owning parts of themselves that
they're not they're not proud of the
female shadow and it's created a really
polarized reaction but as as you say in
the film you want to start a new
conversation between women and men so
hopefully we can start that happening
now but I'd love to hear a bit more
about your background and what you hope
to achieve through the film what what
you want that conversation to look like
so I'm working in conflict resolution
since more than 10 years and mediating
huge conflicts on various levels it's
always the experiences always that our
concepts we are so used to thinking of
either I'm right or you are right either
I'm the victim or I'm the perpetrator
either I'm wrong or you're wrong either
it's my fault or it's you fault
that they're never true and that they
are never leading anywhere I just
realized that it's as true what is true
for any every conflict is just true for
the wounding between men and women and
in the gender war as well and I'm really
dreaming of a new step and a new
dialogue at the cultural level it feels
like we're in a really dysfunctional
relationship between men and women and
that I guess is what kind of where the
film came from and also what we're
trying to achieve through this dialogue
as well so to me it's very interesting
to analyze the wound between men and
women because I think had some special
insights into years of prostitution ten
years ago in my life and when I started
writing a book about it like just one
year ago I realized I'm not the victim
and I
not the aggressor I'm both roads as a
prostitute and I think prostitute is
mainly seen as the victim and the client
of prostitute is mainly seen as an
aggressor and when I started writing
about the clients sexuality as I
remember it I felt we have not address
us they are not the winners and no
client on earth feels like a winner
they are sufferer they suffering so
deeply and are helpless and overwhelmed
and like also victims and I think by
writing this I somehow surprised myself
and then Hanif wrote to me in email
because she read this book when I think
your script just just came out of your
inspiration and I think then we had
these perilous and fear felt this is a
new aspect or dynamics between the sexes
that is as needed as me too and then I
think due to this book and the parallel
to the film we got close with each other
very soon and I was reading the script
and feeling whoa after all the trailer
doing stuff that I'd written this is
really challenging and this is really
taboo and then I need a time to digest
and also I had an immediately immediate
yes at the same time I didn't want to
push myself over my limits because I
felt it's not about my shadow was gone
when I participate in the film it's whoa
I'm more deeply connected with my shadow
it's still there and so I I was I was
happy about the time between getting to
know the script and participating in the
film because it was already a huge
healing journey for me and it went on
after the film I'm so so grateful and
touched by this invitation I think
because it really opens another aspect
of an interesting and lively dialogue
instead of something where we have to
say are we the good ones or the bad ones
and it seems as if collectively I don't
know some something is ready that things
show up now and in the meat too we can
see that really the female wounding has
up I said look what happens we've talked
about this obviously quite a few times
before and what I'm really fascinated
about is that your your background seems
to kind of mirror a lot of the dynamics
that we're seeing now that it kind of
goes back to the 70s the first kind of
move the first kind of eruption of the
women's movement I'll let you kind of
tell the story but it's a really
interesting kind of life story in
experience I come from a different
generation I was living in Berkeley and
Berkeley was also simultaneously going
through the very first first appearance
of a really strong women's movement was
probably the place where it was coming
forth the strongest and that was really
challenging you know also like because I
never thought about objectifying women
or any of the things that was just how
it was you know and then suddenly there
was like thousands of women in Berkeley
who were coming together in getting very
angry and I was just lost with the whole
thing but fortunately there was also the
kind of cutting edge of new therapies
and in her work that was happening and
out of desperation and necessity I found
myself in my very first group which
happened to be a men's group immense
encounter bioenergetic group and what's
in about 20 minutes because it tossed me
into the middle of the room and started
provoking me because I had no access to
my anger and that was what was driving
me crazy and I got him both with living
together with a group of men who
identified themselves we identified
ourselves as feminists it was we were so
we and we created a min Center and we
had a men's radio talk show to talk
about men's issues
but and there were all in response to
the challenges that were coming from the
feminists and basically literally we
were caught with our pants down feeling
very guilty and apologetic and castrated
like we're wrong and I remember one day
in in a meeting just not connecting with
the words everybody was saying and
having this kind of almost like
out-of-body experience in a way where I
felt like I could just see all of us men
and I had this vision that we were all
sitting there sawing off our balls and I
was like shocked by it and I was like
and I realized in that moment that it
wasn't going to it wasn't going to free
me you know and I about after seeing it
no woman pardon nor the women that it
wasn't an answer and I didn't feel all
of a sudden I felt separate from that
group that I felt very connected to and
about 15 minutes later I stood up and
resigned from the group and I just said
there's something going on here and I
didn't name it as castration I didn't
understand that really even at that time
I didn't name it as guilt but I saw it
as guilt and I saw it being turned
everybody was turning against themselves
were so wrong we're so bad and I got up
and I walked out and I went out to
dinner with my mother and I can't became
so interested in this subject or the
healing of Matt of the masculine and the
healing of the feminine that I became a
therapist and it became one of the main
subjects that I specialized in and I
still lead workshops and trainings with
that and it's so so it's the works I
have a big passion for and even so after
all those years
your words were like something I hadn't
before or even allowed myself to
actually conceive of so it was also a
kind of waking up moment for me and and
then was me too coming out and feeling
that anger coming out and having my own
history of realizing how my empowerment
came by really getting in touch with my
anger and letting it come out there was
a big Bravo yes you know about it and at
the same time I think that we need to
come out of the blame culture you know
and we need to come into the responsible
culture and just a little bit of time
that we spent together in the way that
we've been talking and everything just
feels like yes this is the real
conversation between men and women
hasn't happened yet and I hope that as
part of our learning where we're
learning from each other as we talk and
that we're still in that and I don't
want to posture myself as somebody who
has all the answers I don't it's still
it's still a process of Revelation and
learning it's so interesting I just need
to catch that need to stop the blaming
and when I was listening to your story I
immediately thought yes and also the
safe blaming we need to stop the blaming
over there and also the safe self
blaming and in your story you shared how
what you've been experiencing in this
man groups group back then was not so
much okay did we take responsibility for
our shadow it was self blaming and going
into guilt and that's what we women can
do very well as well and I know that
some women out there who have seen the
film are afraid that that's what we were
doing another round of self blaming okay
now it's not blaming now itself blaming
and it's not we don't have a Hydra of
saying sorry for what happened out of a
place of greatness we always learn how
to apologize
from a place of smallness and small
people won't save the earth they won't
be happy they won't contribute to
anything I have to have this incredible
courage of loving myself with all those
shadows yeah and it's when we stop out
of this thing of guilt and fault and go
into just taking responsibility that I
start to be curious about the
conversation yeah it's interesting
there's a there's a big phrase that
became quite popular in the 60s through
the through the women's movement was the
personal is political and what's really
interesting is your film is very
personal very very personal but it's
also putting a finger on one of the kind
of the real source points on the culture
especially coming so soon after me to
the site have kind of so many women
owning their stuff even I I have to
admit when I watched the film when I
watched the poem first time you
delivered it I was immensely touched by
it and I have felt touched by it when
I've watched it but I've also watched it
and felt wow this is so countercultural
for want of a better word it's so
opposite to the narrative that that
we're in as a culture right now that
I've that I've also felt wow it's
unbalanced and I do feel that it's
unbalanced in some way because it has to
be matched by a similar ownership from
the other side certain parts of the
media I would say at the moment of very
have a very ideological perspective a
very sort of feminist ideological
perspective and online there is a kind
of growing anti feminist movement I know
sort of you saw with some of the
comments on YouTube especially and there
is a growing kind of they call the
manosphere online and there's a sense of
any any sign of men kind of owning their
stuff is seen as apologetic it's seen as
and it can be kind of if it's done from
a place of guilt it can be this sort of
self castration it can be this kind of
self negation and I think what's
interesting is can you have ownership of
how we are contributing to the division
between men and women without slipping
into self-hatred without so
into castration without slipping into
apologetic I think that's something that
I find yet that that rebalances the the
film kind of the ownership of a vast off
as men I think it is very possible I
think rather than you know going
together can be these self revelation
and revelation we expands you and makes
you happy and and as you pointed out
anything it is empowering you know it's
like my shadow will play out negatively
as long as I try to keep it in the
closet and it will distort my life it
will bring unhappiness to me and it will
bring unhappiness to the people around
me and it will perpetuate the need then
to blame other people for the
consequences of the ways that they
played out so to me it's very obvious
truth it's still a difficult one because
the shadow is in the shadow it means
it's hidden it means it's not the parent
it's not totally obvious you know and I
don't know if when it ends you know and
when the win the self-discovery process
ends but you know it's it's been with me
for quite a while that understanding
that I need to own my things and I
certainly lived out a with women things
which I feel shamed for and I feel
apology for but I have an understanding
about right now and I'm compassionate
towards myself I didn't get taught I
didn't learn how to be with women I
didn't learn how to be what what how to
deal with this strong sexuality that I
had I didn't and I grew out of a culture
that did objectify women and I came into
certain positions of power where it was
very well I was desirable man and I
could have the women that I wanted and
there were times when you know I abused
that I lied i minimized you know I
didn't
on one hand I've been like this kind of
responsible kind of growth aware guy and
everything but to do it so I can cover
myself look kind of like politically
spiritually correct but I can still tell
a story in a certain way that indicates
more availability then I actually had
and I see myself do that a lot of times
because I wanted to go to bed with
somebody and and and so but I said all
the right things you know but it didn't
you know and there was still a taking
advantage of in some way and it and it
hurt people and I said you know I that
and I tried and it's it's almost like my
brain is conditioned in a certain way to
try to get what I want and to tell the
story that I think will work the best to
get what I want and sometimes it comes
out of my mouth in a way that's not
really totally straight and you know so
that that lying to women within and in
some relationship to sex having sex
telling what happened to a partner when
I come back the the changing of that has
been part of my character for a long
time it's something I just have to
continue to own and every time I do is
such a relaxation because the lie
doesn't really create contact the real
contact that I want there's always a
sensing somewhere that something's a
little bit off and want to just come
clean with it you know you know what I
have to tell you something I was lying
this is the truth this is what I did or
this is what I thought this was my
intention
everybody relaxes in the truth and
everybody stays a little suspicious and
pulled back in the lie and you know I
like this thing can be able to look
straight into the camera over there and
say I have finished with this
and I can't that would be a lie I don't
know I don't know that I am you know I
might have my lust mite over
well me at some moment and I might use
very sophisticated seduction skills that
I have to you know lure somebody in for
my gratification knowing full well that
I don't I'm not going to be with that
person and what I love so much besides
many aspects of your story is it takes
so much time so many centuries so men
who want to learn how to clear their
stuff really clear it and I think they
have this ambition of I want to be
really a cleaned up guy and that's so
great okay then you deserve a few
centuries of studying it every day of
your life and you know what it's not the
women who are worth it who are going to
sleep with you are worth it you're doing
it for yourself yeah and I think this is
a very big key that especially men in
our fast food culture don't learn they
deserve time for learning because this
is deep stuff it's not something that I
can buy it's not something that anybody
learned to perform in and it's not their
guilt that I have to unravel the stuff
and I think then and this is when you
say it like a few minutes before I want
to apologize and it reached me what me
reached is something so touching because
I experienced it so so little from men
in our days they say sorry and they
don't need me they don't need my
reaction they are with themselves they
are with their balls there were some
boundaries they are not something that I
can fall into with you as sorry so I can
get what I want
it touches me so deeply and this is not
because you learned it yesterday but
because you started studying at 40 years
ago and I just want to say thank you for
that because what I experienced in my
nervous system and I would add to
personal is political personal is
collective what I experienced is
something that really matters to me and
I think this is something that I might
say to many women in the collective
thank you something more that I could
feel I could feel the relaxation in my
nervous system when you were just saying
that's the truth and in allowing
yourself to say I cannot say into the
camera that is all heal now I'm clean
now I'm continuously doing this work and
owning and trying to be as honest as I
can
gives me the allowance to be allowed to
learn to and I want to learn to be more
and more and more clear with my truth
and my boundaries instead of going into
the seduction and manipulation games we
have learned and I cannot promise that I
will do in every moment and I will not
step back into it in moments and thus I
do understand a Stan man's mistrust I do
understand that it's not easy to trust
as women I do understand and I even
can't say me honestly me you can trust
always I can't I can't
sometimes I can't even trust myself and
I think it's really important that we
acknowledge that it's part of a learning
curve and you can't see further ahead of
the learning curve than where you are
right now but that you recognize the
history of it and who knows what the
next challenges are going to be one
thing I definitely realize is that in
the moment where we just decide and
commit both to wanting to learn owning
that we make mistakes that we fall back
and that we are curious about finding
out what it is what what is acting out
what are we doing when I feel that both
sides are curious about it then I I
start to become really alive and really
interested and really interested in the
relation and really interested in the
dialogue in the conversation it's
interesting comparing two to you like
we're from different generations yeah
and I was raised by a very feminist
family by a feminist mother a FEMINIST
father and my I think the way that that
that I've behaved in relationships has
been much more holding myself back and
the lying has been a kind of lie of
omission all the time it's been not
fully showing up not fully telling the
truth not kind of taking on this kind of
feeling of I'm completely responsible
for the way that my partner feels so not
being honest about the way I was feeling
and stringing stringing women along of
kind of internalizing this this feeling
of I'm completely responsible for
everything that they feel and then not
really being honest and being in
relationships for longer than I should
be and not being honest about what I'm
feeling so when I look at the me to
movement and that it's a lot of kind of
men the moments like men acting out and
being sexually predatory I didn't
experience that I don't think that was
my stuff and I don't think that's a lot
of guys from from my generation stuff
and a lot of them were actually brought
up in a different environment and a lot
of it was feeling a sense of shame
around themselves as men and not fully
showing up for that reason at least that
is something that I have started to
experience and in my work with my
client's etc etc that as I said in the
beginning in the moment where I started
to be interested in my shadow and when I
started to feel more empowered and more
loving towards myself I started to feel
really compassion for the role I could
see wow it has to be difficult to grow
up as a boy and to become a man nowadays
because the narrative of men are
perpetrators men are violators men are
abusers is so huge and out of good
reasons of course it's the this does not
come out of nothing but no man is born
as a abuser and other aggressor and has
a problem it oh it's a biological
problem so yes and you get born and
you'd grow up with these images of
manhood and I think this is something
that raffia talks about really well that
if as a man you grow up feeling that you
then suppress a lot of the kind of the
natural aggression or the natural kind
of feelings you you don't you you very
much don't want to be like those other
guys and actually that leads to a sort
of shadow of perverted aggression so
when we hear the word aggression and
male aggression we think about men
taking their gun or taking the penis and
raping woman and I think these are
perverted expressions of an aggression
that the men had to suppress before it
got into this form so even though our
language is very it's it's very subtle
what what we are looking for in the
first place is an instinctual anger of
protecting boundaries and that's for the
sake of peace and for the sake of war
between the sexes so yeah and that's so
interesting the way you say that because
what I work with a lot of times with men
is that they they have rejected a side
of their own masculinity like the roots
of their investment because they want to
be like anything but like all those guys
who they see as responsible for the
problems and so they and and they think
that that's a level of aggression and
violence and sexual abuse and so they
repress that side and of course then it
gets acted out it comes out and all
kinds of things and a lot of times what
I'm doing in groups with men is getting
men to go in and really feel that layer
of the masculine whether is the level of
aggression and frustration and anger and
hatred and encourage them to just allow
it to come out and rather than that
overwhelm
their personality like they're afraid
and then becoming that way they find
that it's actually not that much it's
like it's a lair but as long as you deny
that lair
you know you you lose your roots and you
lose your instinctive connection to
masculinity and into the truth that you
could express in your sexuality you know
and so that's a big part of flick the
men's work I do is to get men to go into
that culture creates the specific male
shadow of aggression and it's like every
shadow of the thing is this and it's
healthy and it's good but a shadow is a
monster and then you say you want me
touching this monster no way you say
honey trust me I'm doing this for 40
years it's worth it every time I do it
and then you say hey come on I see I
think every also with female rage I
think this is not that big difference
whenever I go really infrared and really
enter and guide stay with my body I find
myself to be the most peaceful being on
earth the last thing that I plant I just
plan to somehow survive this wave of
rage and then wow I'm okay you okay it's
quite a shock how positive it is to
discharge suppressed aggression because
this because this thing about the
repressed or the repressed aggression
which then as any any shadow does then
plays out I think is actually the
unspoken dynamic behind a lot of the me
to stuff that we've seen because a lot
it's come out that a lot of the people
who were accused of acting out in ways
during me to identify themselves as male
feminists they identified themselves as
not those kind of guys and if you
identify yourself as I'm not that kind
of guy then you're suppressing this
thing and it comes out sideways
and I think this is this is part of on a
cultural level I think unless we realize
this that actually we need to encourage
men to embrace their masculinity to live
that out to be in in a full way then
they are discharging it they're not
pushing it down into the cellar and then
it comes out
sideways and I think as a culture where
we're actually probably going to
encourage more of that kind of stuff
because we're teaching men to be ashamed
of their sexuality we're teaching men to
be ashamed of their masculine aggression
I think that's actually going to have
the the the reverse effect to the one
that we think and I want to add that
when a group of men go through that and
it's something I would try and bring in
rather early in a men's group they come
into a relaxation and like you said
peacefulness and and this thing of male
bonding becomes very real a support for
each other and a love and a kindness
and and and the almost the cessation of
a certain kind of competition that is
there when somebody feels castrated or
when somebody is not empowered and
they're always having to prove
themselves and they come in as brothers
and support and it's one of the most
beautiful things that happens in men's
group it isn't that they arrive okay
this is home and I'm a I'm a beast I'm a
rapist I'm a killer I'm I think it's
quite the opposite they go oh god I feel
so good and I love being a man and this
and they can feel their legs and they
can feel their balls and they can feel
that kind of connection and it's a kind
of simple healing in fact of all of a
tremendous amount of what's been
absorbed from the culture which is
making masculinity so toxic and and I
want to say that it that it's also right
to really challenge the masculinity in
the way that it acts out with the way
that acts out when this when a man is
castrated and when he hasn't owned as
part of himself he really is a bit of a
monster and I think the big
misunderstanding collectively is that we
mistake this expression of distorted
castrated masculinity as masculinity so
many when I listen to many feminist
women not all of them of course many it
sounds as if
that was the essence of masculinity and
thus we have to fight it and this is a
huge misunderstanding because this is
not natural masculinity these is already
coming out of this castration of losing
access to natural masculinity and also
same as for for as women to you to to
natural power I think both femininity I
was so turned off of being a woman when
I thought what the sky tree offers me as
typical feminine it's it's the loser cut
who who should want to have tits nobody
on earth it's just being being the
secondary class of human beings and so
when I started to question is this right
or am i right and have every right on
earth to unravel my kind of femininity I
became curious and I think this is so
important for men truth they want to
gain back their masculine essence and so
they have to be curious about what comes
up in themselves when they allow to set
boundaries to this conditioning or the
cultural imprint what masculinity means
so it's almost like we need true words
we need are we talking about this
masculinity or the true masculinity of
boy psychology and man psychology a lot
of people divide it into that so a lot
of what people are protesting against or
attacking is boy psychology rather than
man psychology it's not fully and in
both cases I think like a real rite of
passage at the time of life when were
coming into puberty were you're welcomed
into the feminine and into womanhood and
you're the secrets and mysteries of it
are revealed to you by elder women and
the same for men my life would have been
different God if I had if I had gotten
the teaching in that way of what it what
does it mean and I felt included and I
felt the support I felt like a group of
men or just even my father you know had
my back come were there for me you know
it would have changed everything you
know I just I was so I really the amount
of suffering and and pain and loss and
being alone with it and just completely
confused I would like to come back to
what you have been sharing because I
think it's really interesting you have
been sharing that your personal
experience is quite different in a
different generation it has not been as
much conditioning let's say of women are
objects has more been you have to care
for women from women's emotion for you
are responsible or let's say guilty when
a woman feels bad this kind of stuff and
I imagine that this brings along a lot
of holding back of own needs wishes
whatever truthful and that this can
bring a lot of rage to I'm curious I'm
curious to hear about you is there right
about that understand what what is your
experience with that
well yeah I don't know how much of that
is particular to my upbringing because
my mother was often depressed and I
think a lot of children take on if they
have a depressed parent that it's their
fault so a lot of that could be tied in
with it as well but I also know from the
inner work that I've done and I know
you've done a lot of inner work as well
if you dig down
it's almost universal that you have some
kind of anger towards your parents you
were in this kind of very you you you
pretty much you all of your emotions you
you kind of put onto your parents they
were the world and they never they were
they were there they weren't there and
when they weren't there we all have this
kind of infantile rage I think we all
have on some level inside us and I think
getting that out in some way is kind of
an essential
part of of getting more healthy as a as
an adult but also going into that kind
of inner work what I found really
interesting was how much more difficult
it is to identify the mother stuff than
it is to identify the father stuff I
often and I've seen it with other people
in these kind of processes as well it's
it's it's quite easy sometimes to see
what my father did this my father did
that he was there he wasn't there he was
an alcoholic it was whatever and you can
kind of quite easily identify and it
seems much more easy to process whereas
the mother stuff I found far more
difficult to see I'm far more difficult
to clear because a lot of the time it
comes with these sort of feelings of
what it would be so wrong to feel angry
towards your mother it would be so bad
to feel that towards your mother and
I've I've seen yeah I certainly for
myself I found it much more difficult to
see you identify it and then to kind of
work with it than with the father stuff
you just touched something though that I
think for myself personally and I see it
with other men ties the story of the
mother and lack of power and the men
together and that has been this feeling
that you're become very very sensitive
to your mother's feelings and the
changes of mood and whatever is
happening in the house and it creates a
kind of pleaser mentality in a way
that's trying to damage control women
and I've noticed in my relationships I
carry that sensitivity it's like my
mother was mostly really quite a bright
and happy person but when she would go
you'd feel the air change you know and
there's something going on and then I I
see myself getting activated in a way
that I become a pleaser
it's then what can I do in order and bit
underneath it I'm trying to change her
I'm trying to damage control the the
emotional woman you know and and what it
brings
and I know it from my own experience and
I see it mother thinks it brings out the
contempt of the woman because the women
hate because I become regressing to a
boy in that moment I'm afraid basically
of the feminine feelings and that may be
some kind of negativity is gonna come up
and so I start trying to find out what's
wrong or make things right or please
or go to my mind and try and talk to her
talk some sense into her and damage
control the whole thing but it's all
motivated for by my discomfort of that
situation and it's a it's a real
challenge for me even today if I feel
that my woman is going through something
and to let her be you know and and not
come in with oak and I you know start
doing nice things for her or or trying
to talk her out of her feelings yeah how
can I fix it trying to fix a woman you
know and and it and it's a sure thing to
bring out the woman sword that wants to
you know whack my balls off you know
because they I think because I don't
think a woman wants a boy and so to
really investigate that whole part you
know of the fear of women's emotions and
the fear and and risk a woman's
rejection and anger is a big step in
growing up to being a man and I and it's
it's a scary one to risk the woman's
anger you know and rejection and if but
if we don't we become pleasers and we're
not really present then as the men and
we're not really there and then and then
totally totally and it's the register
ends the right yeah you can manipulate
it and you can castrate and reject
usually we do both usually we do both
usually we do both first women
manipulated and then wicked yeah and so
for me it's a real and that that's part
of the complexity of the relationship of
the mother because the mother was
holding the basic energy of the house
and of course I want to be in the loving
happy merged relaxed space and when all
of a sudden the vibe in the house starts
to get tense and the chill comes in and
then I know something bad is going to
happen I know fights gonna erupt between
my mother and my father maybe my
father's late coming home from work
which means he stopped off to have a
drink which means my mom is really
activated and it's gonna be a fight then
I'm on alert my whole nervous system is
is on alert then and I'm trying to
damage control it and I've lost myself
you know and it was a very real fear as
a kid but I've somehow to confront that
place as a man and see it and then say
what I really feel you know instead of
trying to manipulate because that's
where the manipulation goes in and just
come out and ask really straight hey
what's going on right now you know and
be there and be present and grounded in
in in the mask on and recognize that
something's happening and not be in
trying to fix it or be in judgment of it
but be actually really curious does that
work Kirsten I'm really curious what's
going on right now and it's so
interesting for me it's so interesting
to hear and to realize how this having
learned that somehow manipulate the
situation and the other person is the
only way to damage control or to is
mutual is because we as girls have
learned that from our mother to maybe
slightly different reasons I can
for myself and I know this is true for
many women I know that we have not
learned from our mothers that a girl and
a woman can have clear boundaries and
say what she thinks and what she means
and say no and stand up for what is
right for me I have not learned that I
had no role model for that it's always
now trying to make it right for everyone
else
and in order to get it at least a little
bit right for yourself to manipulate and
it's always trying to find safety by
going through the outer world and that's
always the wrong first step I have to be
safe with myself and I think this is
also an insight where it's like it's
really 10 deaths at the same time it's
like somebody asks me what do you feel
and I try to train it what does you want
to hear how sick is that
but how normal how collective how deeply
am I not in touch with myself so I'm not
out of touch with myself when my women
gets a woman gets grumpy I've heard of
touch with my life like all the time
so this is something of where we really
I think get humble and wise around how
deeps wounding is and how big the gifts
that we can get on this way because what
I notice is that if I don't lose my
ground and I don't go into the pleasing
boy and I don't go into the damage
controlling thing and I stay grounded in
myself and I ask for granted plus hey
what's going on I find women generally
will go the sense that safety from the
grounded Mexican and they'll go in their
share very honestly and they'll tell me
yeah no and it's really because in and
it's the easy conversation and then
rather than have a long complicated kind
of thing that swims in the
maresi swampy territory for a few days
it's over in a couple minutes and again
I feel in the kind of you asking what's
going on that I won't be able to get you
with my manipulation so I can stop my
drama queen behavior right at this
moment and to be honest it's a relief
but I don't get this exit normally
because you always
going on like honey can I be a better
person and then you stop crying
and so it's so interesting around men
with healthy boundaries it's it's a high
way to connect a feeling it's the it's
the paradoxes that by saying it's only
when you're prepared to say something
that might make someone dislike you or
make a woman dislike you you make a
woman reject you that you actually
become safe enough to trust and it's
it's as you've said it it's the growing
up from a boy to a man being prepared to
say something that might make a woman
reject you and being grounded enough to
be able to receive not happy reactions
in the person yes yeah I think even
retraction rejected of being the fear of
being rejected from the woman is a fear
of death because it's your mother
rejecting you I think rejection itself
isn't dangerous enough I think it's it's
not something I'm not love but I'm
threatened to death I think there's some
sense it is an existential thing you
really take it way way back yeah it
manifests this is like rejection or so
it's also that's maybe I'm the cause of
it or and then you enter into a very
complex relationship with a feminine in
that whole thing whereas you as I said a
minute ago and you confirm it it's
actually very simple
but also from an evolutionary level it's
that women hold the key for men men's
jeans to go into the next generation
so being rejected by a woman is being
rejected by its life by existence
and on some level I think that's that's
absolutely true I think that's the level
of that's the level of existential
terror that a lot of men have asking
women out that in some sense they're
standing in for the world they're
standing in for nature they're standing
in for existence itself so it's not just
a male ego thing it's really an urgent
instinctual threat of yes or no life or
death I want to this something else that
struck me recently as always thinking
about your film Hannah is that and you
also saw this with some of the reactions
to it
was quite a few especially on YouTube
there were some reactions from guys who
I'd say to the mug town men going their
own way or men's rights activists saying
too late ladies you you won't trick us
again all of this really sort of toxic
pretty misogynistic comments and there
are online there are quite a lot of
places that where talk about women
degenerates into this very sort of toxic
or very misogynistic very very
suspicious very misogynistic place and
what I found really interesting when I
was thinking about your film is that
because there is very little discussion
of the female shadow in culture the only
place that I think a lot of guys who've
maybe been hurting relationships
find it is on these websites so suddenly
the only place that you ever hear anyone
talking about while women are women can
be manipulative women can be bitch's
women can be like and behave badly if
the only place that people find it is on
these websites then what I think will
happen is that people will then get more
and more radicalized because on this
websites it's not that women can behave
like this it's women always behave like
this women always will ditch you for a
more more attractive man they will you
can't trust what they say there's all of
these kind of really yeah and it feels
like you expressing both of you
expressing the the fact of the female
shadow and bringing that somehow more
into the conversation is really
essential to because otherwise the only
place that you can find it is where the
conversation goes toxic and making that
conversation much more mainstream I
think is essential really essential to
to try and because otherwise it's it's
really unbalanced yes and I was really
surprised - honestly I discovered these
men's rights movement and men going
their own way thanks to the film and the
reactions to the film I didn't know
anything about it I had learned a lot
about men's moon
I had started to see how difficult it is
also to grow up as a man in this society
and in this world but I didn't know that
there could be and of course I knew
about devaluation of women by men but
that there can be so much hurt and hate
against women as you find it on these
websites I didn't even know I was not
aware of and it's shocking some way it's
really shocking but it's also touching
because it it shows how deep the
wounding is and something that stroked
me is that I I start to see a parallel
and a parallel between where feminism
has partly gone where me too has partly
gun means turned into something toxic
turned instead of standing up for our
rights and our boundaries starting to
fight all men collectively sitting in we
are the victims we are the poor ones and
you are all all the bad ones
and it struck me to see that these men
who write in that way in these internet
pages etc are doing exactly the same
they saying we men are the victims and
all women are evil and now we have to
fight the women instead of standing up
and saying stop here I have a clear
boundary because not all men are evil
and we have our wounds we have
experience we have had a lot of bad
experiences that is great but but this
going into a victim's hole and pointing
the finger finger and fighting
collectively the other sex I can see it
on both sides and it's not going
anywhere it's as Patrick's would work it
would have worked already yes that's
really like flipping it around it just
changes the color of the same problem we
won't get anywhere with the same metrics
with the same thinking and yet and so
but it's also true for both sides that I
see the pain where it comes from I see
I've seen it for a woman first to be
honest
but I see it there now too and I see
many things they have gone through and
I'm happy what you have pointed out that
yes that this film might be one
contribution I hope it's just the
beginning of a new conversation a
beginning of a contribution to offering
space for having these conversations in
the more mature way and in a more
constructive way and I am actually
touched by quite some feedbacks I get
from man who have experienced very badly
but have very bad experiences many wrote
about their experience in divorce not
being allowed to see their kids having
been well even also I received letters
of man saying I have been not not even
only emotionally but also physically
abused in my marriage I have stayed
because I have two wonderful kids I have
a lot of heavy experiences and I guess
that a man going into these movements
men going their own way many of them
have these experiences and have never
found a place to express their hurt and
I'm I'm really touched and happy that
thanks to this film man show up and
write about this experiences without
hatred but with hope they wrote thank
you so much
I hope again that woman maybe can even
love me as a man I had I read this Miami
it's touching
it's wow and I guess my hope for this
film and the subsequent work and the
work that's happening anna frebel wisdom
is that it will encourage healing and
offer possibilities other than blame and
victimhood and without judgment towards
the people who've taken these very
strong positions because we don't know
what happened to them you know there
they form their personalities the way
that they did and they came to these
beliefs out of real experiences and so
there has to be a certain level of
compassion but just to even get the
possibility that is possible to have
open honest conversations where people
on their shadow side I know from my work
with people is really a route towards
healing now how quickly that is taken up
or how broadly that is embraced remains
to be seen you know but I that's why I
respect so much the work that you're
doing right now and going around and
talking to all these people who I think
really do want the healing to happen it
really you want I mean how much richer
better life be if we really can open up
and talk and share and being how much
more joyful and I mean it's just so
obvious I want to repeat what you have
been saying in the beginning I would
love to invite everyone to start to to
do these steps and not for the others me
as a woman I am not doing it for you I'm
really doing it for myself and you
should do it for yourself and not for us
because it's so freeing it is stepping
out of a victim's place it's the best
thing I could ever have done for myself
that's the truth and my truth is my
heart once to love and if I stay in the
victims place stay in the blaming place
I don't allow my heart to love and I
suffer from it maybe you do but in the
first place me I suffer from it